Guide to the Mark Plotkin papers, 1953-2018 MS2370
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mark Plotkin papers
1953-2018
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2370
7 Linear Feet
This collection contains handwritten commentaries, typed commentary, published articles from multiple newspapers and personal documents from the career of Mark Plotkin. Plotkin was most well known for his career as a political commentator and analyst primarily on the radio and on TV. These appearances were local and international (CBC-Canadian Broadcasting Company and CTV-Canadian Television Commentary). Plotkin was the political analyst for WAMU, an NPR affiliate, from 1982-2002. After leaving WAMU Plotkin was the political analyst for WTOP (all news radio station) from 1989-2012. Plotkin has also been active in print media, writing articles for The Washington Post, The Georgetowner, and Legal Times. Plotkin was outspoken about his beliefs supporting self governance for D.C., full congressional representation for D.C. in Congress and statehood for D.C..
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three series; radio commentary, news articles, personal documents and research. WTOP commentaries by month (as WAMU.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mark Plotkin, January 30, 2018 (2018.006). Second accession in 2019 (2019.100)
Biographical / Historical
Mark Plotkin was a journalist, political commentator, columnist, analyst and radio host, most well known for his commentary in the Washington D.C. area. A graduate from the University of Chicago High School. Plotkin first came to Washington to attend the George Washington University where he would earn his bachelor's degree in American history in 1969. After completing his degree, Plotkin taught public school in Chicago and Washington until 1971 when his attention turned to politics.
Since the late 1960s, Plotkin was active in the Washington political scene. During the 1972 elections, Plotkin was an advance man and congressional district coordinator for Edmund Muskie, Eugene McCarthy and George McGovern. From 1976-1984 Plotkin was the deputy finance director for Morris Udall (1976), Ted Kennedy (1980) and for Gary Hart's presidential campaign (1984). Plotkin served as an elected member of the Advisory Neighborhood Commission from 1981-1985 and chaired the commission for two years. Plotkin, was elected to the D.C. Democratic state committee from 1984-1989.
Plotkin was most well known for his career as a radio commentator for WAMU and WTOP radio. Plotkin's career started at WAMU, an NPR affiliate, in 1989 and continued there until 2002. In 2002, Plotkin moved from WAMU to WTOP, all news station. At WTOP, Plotkin co-hosted a weekly political radio show which he used as a platform for advocacy of voting rights for D.C. residents and D.C. statehood. Plotkin left WTOP in 2012.
In addition to his radio commentating, Plotkin was also a columnist for Legal Times, The Georgetowner, and and an op-ed contributor to The Washington Post. Presently Plotkin is a contributor to BBC on American politics and a columnist to TheHill.com. Plotkin is a winner of the Edward R. Murrow award for Excellence in Writing.
Mark Plotkin died at age 72 in 2019.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains handwritten and typed radio commentaries, newspaper articles, photographs, correspondence, biographical records, DC election materials including bumper stickers and buttons, engagement calendars, and film from Mark Plotkin. The documents date from 1953-2018.
Journalism; Washington (D.C.); Statehood (American politics) -- Washington (D.C.); Radio; Washington (D.C.) Politics and government; Political campaigns; City council members -- Washington (D.C.); Political activists; Schools -- Washington (D.C.); Home rule; Political conventions; United States. Congress. House--District of Columbia voting rights; Maryland--Politics and government; Virginia--Politics and government; Neighborhoods; United States--Politics and government; Campaign funds; Mayors--United States; Legislators--United States; Governors--United States; Judicial power; Federal government; Fiscal policy; Plotkin, Mark
- Radio commentary, 1989-2012; Series 1
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the handwritten and typed notes from Mark Plotkin's radio commentaries. The material is from Plotkin's time at WAMU and WTOP.
  - WAMU commentary, 1989; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - WAMU Commentary, 1989; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - WAMU commentary, 1990; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - WAMU commentary, 1991; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - WAMU commentary, 1992; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - WAMU commentary, 1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - WAMU commentary, 1994; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - WAMU commentary, 1995; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - WAMU commentary, 1996; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - WAMU commentary, 1997; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 January; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 February; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 March; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 April; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 May; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 June; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 July; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 August; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 September; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 October; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 November; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - WAMU commentary, 1998 December; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - WAMU Commentary, 1998-2001; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 January; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 February; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 March; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 April; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 May; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 June; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 July; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 August; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 September; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 October; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 November; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - WAMU commentary, 1999 December; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - WAMU Commentary, 1999-2002; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - WAMU commentary, 2000; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - WAMU Commentary, 2000 January - March; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - WAMU Commentary, 2000 April - July; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - WAMU Commentary, 2000 July - September; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - WAMU Commentary, 2000 October - December; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - WAMU Commentary, 2001 January - May; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - WAMU Commentary, 2001 June - December; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - WTOP commentary, 2002; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - WAMU Commentary, 2002 January; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - WAMU Commentary, 2002 February; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - WAMU Commentary, 2002 March; MS2370 Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - WTOP commentary, 2003; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - WTOP commentary, 2004; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - WTOP commentary, 2005; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - WTOP commentary, 2006; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - WTOP commentary, 2007; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - WTOP commentary, 2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - WTOP commentary, 2009; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - WTOP commentary, 2010; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - WTOP commentary, 2011; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - WTOP commentary, 2012; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Radio commentary, Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Newspaper articles, 1990-2017; Series 2; 1 Linear Feet
  This series contains the published articles and opinion editorials from Mark Plotkin. The articles come from publications such as Legal Times, The Georgetowner and The Washington Post. The documents date from 1990-2017.
  - Legal Times index, 1990-1998; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 1)
  - Legal Times, Undated; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 2)
  - Legal Times, 1990; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 3)
  - Legal Times, 1991; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 4)
  - Legal Times, 1992; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 5)
  - Legal Times, 1993; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 6)
  - Legal Times, 1994; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 7)
  - Legal Times, 1995; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 8)
  - Legal Times, 1996; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 9)
  - Legal Times, 1997; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 10)
  - Legal Times, 1998; Series 2 (Flat box 4, Folder 11)
  - The Washington Post opinion editorials, 1983-2012; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Georgetowner, 2014-2016; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Georgetowner, 2016-2017; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Downtowner, 2003 October; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Progressive Review, 1986 March; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Legal Times articles, 1990-1998; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous articles, Undated; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Personal documents and research, 1953-2018; Series 3
  This series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  This series contains personal documents, such as photographs, and research on the U.S. Capitol as well as records related to DC politics including Plotkin's run for office. There are also press credentials for political and sports events. Documents date from 1953-2018.
  - Campaign and election materials, 1982-1991, 2008, undated; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Certificate membership to the D.C. Advisory Committee on City-Wide Telecommunications System for Mark Plotkin, 1985 September 19; MS2370 Series 3 (Flat box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence related to elections, 1977-1991; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Credentials D.C. Delegate Constitutional Convention, 2016; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - D.C. Democratic State Committee, 1987-1989; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Election information kit, 1990 November 06; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Engagement calendars, 1985, 1987; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Engagement calendars, 1988-1990; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Engagement calendars, 1991-1993; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Engagement calendars, 1994, 1996; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Engagement calendars, 1997-1999; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Engagement calendars, 2000-2002; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Engagement calendars, 2003-2005; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Engagement calendars, 2006-2007; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Engagement calendars, 2008-2009; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Engagement calendars, 2010-2011; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Engagement calendars, 2012-2013; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Engagement calendars, 2014-2015; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Engagement Calendars, 2017-2019; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Film cannister/film, Undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Fiscal prospects for the State of New Columbia, 1986 September 11; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Harold Brazil campaign, 1990; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Invitations, 1977-2001; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Mayflower Hotel photograph, 2000 June 15; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Personal materials, 1953-1983; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Personal materials, 1983-1993; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Personal materials, 1994-2018, undated; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Photographs and invitation: WAMU roast of Mark Plotkin, 2000; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Photographs: family and work, Undated; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Press passes Republican political conventions, 1996-2016; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Press passes Democrat political conventions, 1980-2016; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Press credential politics and sports events, 1992-2012; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Political buttons and bumper stickers, Undated; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Political posters [for Mark] and districting map, Circa 1990s - Circa 2008; MS2370 Series 3 (Flat box 14, Folder 3)
  - Remarks of Curtis Etherly Jr., Undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Sharon Pratt Dixon campaign, 1990; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - T-shirt: No Taxation Without Representation, Circa 2000; MS2370 Series 3 (Flat box 14, Item 1)
  - U.S. Capitol research documents, 2002; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - WAMU roast of Mark Plotkin, 2000 June 15; MS2370 Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 2)